<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://esmaxness.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://esmaxness.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-09-28T08:56:02+00:00</updated><id>https://esmaxness.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Traffic Differentiation with RINA QoS Cubes</title><link href="https://esmaxness.github.io/blog/2023/rinaQoS/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Traffic Differentiation with RINA QoS Cubes"/><published>2023-09-27T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-27T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://esmaxness.github.io/blog/2023/rinaQoS</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://esmaxness.github.io/blog/2023/rinaQoS/"><![CDATA[<p>During my summer holidays, Id went to Brazil. I landed at Guarulhos airport in Sao Paulo. My friend Joao picked me up from the airport to his home to enjoy a long summer holiday. On the way to his house, we were stuck in a high-density vehicular traffic jam. Joao explained that Sao Paulo is high-density populated, and the bottlenecks are always in every avenue in Sao Paulo. The Sao Paulo traffic jams make it challenging to move from one point to another, and it causes delays and poor quality of life for Sao Paulo citizens. I took advantage of this to explain to Joao what is my research about. I am working on the Recursive Inter-Networking Architecture (RINA), which can classify network traffic jams using policies. If Sao Paulo implements RINA QoS Cubes Policies, it could reduce the bottlenecks and the delays.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-"> </div> <div class="col-"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/SaoPaulo-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/SaoPaulo-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/SaoPaulo-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/SaoPaulo.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-4"> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Traffic jam in Sao Paulo, Brazil. </div> <h4 id="how-does-rina-provide-traffic-differentiation">How does RINA provide traffic differentiation?</h4> <p>RINA provides for Quality of Services (QoS) through QoS Cubes. The QoS Cubes are traffic classes that are employed to clasificate the Service Data Units (SDUs) that get into the DIF. This classification depends on several parameters (delay, packet loss, datarate, and among others). Each QoS Cube has asociated a policy for dealing with for dealing with flow control, routing, forwarding, scheduling, and congestion management. The DIFs provide the same type of service but with different characteristics depending on statistical bounds on metrics like data rate, latency, losses, and others. The application will request a service from the DIF based on its requirements (data rate, latency, losses, among others), and the DIF provides a flow with the QoS cube that matches these requirements. Each flow allocation request must contain as metadata the application requirements. The higher level DIF requests flow with a particular QoS to lower-level DIFs until the physical media is reached.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-"> </div> <div class="col-"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/RINA_QoS_Cube2-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/RINA_QoS_Cube2-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/RINA_QoS_Cube2-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/RINA_QoS_Cube2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-4"> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Traffic Differentiation with RINA QoS Cubes. </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="rina-iot"/><category term="rina"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[what is a RINA QoS Cube?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">RINAsense architecture</title><link href="https://esmaxness.github.io/blog/2023/rinasense/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RINAsense architecture"/><published>2023-08-01T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-01T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://esmaxness.github.io/blog/2023/rinasense</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://esmaxness.github.io/blog/2023/rinasense/"><![CDATA[<p>One of the my main contributions to achieve the TERMINET objectives was the design and development of a RINA architecture for embedded devices to enable RINA networks in IoT environments. Achieving this goal was not trivial because of IoT heterogeneity and IoT limitations on resources. The inherent IoT heterogeneity introduces a high complication to design and implement RINA modules for embedded systems. IoT has many technological IoT platforms, protocols, and wireless communication technologies, so the RINA modules should be able to adapt to IoT technologies. Also, IoT devices are resource-constrained in terms of CPU, memory, network and energy consumption. So, a deep analysis was required to understand the possible limitations of RINA in resource-constrained devices.</p> <p>The RINAsense architecture is proposed to implement RINA in resource-constrained devices. The RINAsense architecture is organized in layers.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-"> </div> <div class="col-"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/RINAsenseArquitectura-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/RINAsenseArquitectura-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/RINAsenseArquitectura-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/RINAsenseArquitectura.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-4"> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> RINAsense architecture for IoT environments. </div> <h4 id="architecture-layers">Architecture Layers</h4> <ul> <li>Data Link Layer: oversees moving data into and out of a wireless link in a network. It comprises wireless technologies used in IoT environments. It provides services to the above DIFs to move data between sensors or through a RINA-based IoT gateway to edge nodes or the cloud.</li> <li>RINA Layer: provides all RINA components to implement a system with RINA networking capabilities. This layer provides functionalities for transmitting data, controlling the data transmission, and managing the RINA network.</li> <li>Application Layer: delivers applications or services to sense the environment(sensors) and make some response (actuators).</li> <li>OS and Abstraction Layer: provides a runtime environment to control the previous layers' functionalities. These tasks share a single processing core using the Free Real Time Operating System (FreeRTOS). This layer relies on FreeRTOS because of its extension portability over several microcontroller platforms. In addition, this layer provides a portability sublayer to allow writing cross-platform software to control devices based on the IoT development framework for ESP-IDF, Arduino, or Linux.</li> </ul> <p>A instance of the RINAsense architecture is available as open source in i2CAT <a href="https://github.com/Fundacio-i2CAT/rinasense">Github Reposiroty</a>. More details and experimental tests can be found in the <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/10084905/">RINAsense conference paper</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="rina-iot"/><category term="rina"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[innovative architecture to prototype IoT devices in RINA networks]]></summary></entry></feed>